I remember as a child,
أتذكر عندما كنت طفلاً،
my first tool I built was actually a microscope
أول أداة صنعتها كانت في الواقع "مجهر"
that I built by stealing lenses from my brother's eyeglasses.
صنعته بالعدسات التي سرقتها من نظارات أخي.
He wasn't that thrilled.
وهو لم يكن سعيدًا بذلك.
But, you know, maybe because of that moment,
ولكن، كما تعلمون، ربما بسبب تلك اللحظة،
30 years later,
بعد 30 عاماً،
I'm still making microscopes.
ما زلت أصنع المَجاهِر.
And the reason I built these tools is for moments like this.
وسَبب صُنعي لهذه الأدوات هو من أجل لحظات كهذه.
Manu Prakash: This is a school in the Bay Area.
مانو براكاش: هذه مدرسة في منطقة الخليج.
(Video) MP: The living world far supersedes our imagination
(فيديو) مانو براكاش: العالم الحي يفوق تصورنا
of how things actually work.
حول كيفية عمل الأشياء.
(Video) Boy: Oh my God!
(فيديو) صبي: يا إلهي!
MP: Right -- oh my God!
مانو براكاش: حقاً.. يا إلهي!
I hadn't realized this would be such a universal phrase.
لم أكن أدرك أن هذه العبارة ستكون بهذه العالمية.
Over the last two years,
على مَدى العامين الماضيين،
in my lab,
في مُختبري،
we built 50,000 Foldscopes
صَنعنا 50,000 فولدسكوب
and shipped them to 130 countries in the world,
وقمنا بشحنها إلى 130 دولة في العالم،
at no cost to the kids we sent them to.
دون أي تكلفة للأطفال الذين أرسلت لهم.
This year alone,
في هذا العام وحده،
with the support of our community,
وبدعم من مجتمعنا،
we are planning to ship a million microscopes
نخطط لشحن مليون مجهر
to kids around the world.
للأطفال في مختلف أنحاء العالم.
What does that do?
ماذا يعني أن تفعل هذا؟
It creates an inspiring community of people around the world,
إنه يخلق أناساً مُلهمين في شتى أنحاء العالم،
learning and teaching each other,
يتعلمون ويعلمون بعضهم البعض
from Kenya to Kampala to Kathmandu to Kansas.
من كينيا إلى كمبالا ومن إلى كاتماندو إلى كانساس.
And one of the phenomenal things that I love about this
وواحدةٌ من الأشياء الهائلة التي أحببتها
is the sense of community.
هي الإحساس بالانتماء للمجتمع.
There's a kid in Nicaragua
هناك طفل في نيكاراغوا
teaching others how to identify mosquito species that carry dengue
يقوم بتعليم الآخرين كيفية تحديد أنواع البعوض التي تحمل حمى الدنك
by looking at the larva under a microscope.
من خلال النظر إلى اليرقات تحت المجهر.
There's a pharmacologist who came up with a new way
وهناك صيدلي جاء بطريقة جديدة
to detect fake drugs anywhere.
للكشف عن الأدوية المغشوشة في أي مكان.
There is a girl who wondered:
هناك فتاة تساءلت:
"How does glitter actually work?"
"كيف يحدث البريق؟"
and discovered the physics of crystalline formation in glitter.
واكتشفت فيزياء التكوين البلوري في البريق.
There is an Argentinian doctor
هناك طبيب أرجنتيني
who's trying to do field cervical cancer screening with this tool.
حاول فحص سرطان عنق الرحم بواسطة هذه الأداة.
And yours very truly found a species of flea
أما أنا فوجدت فصيلة من البراغيث
that was dug inside my heel in my foot one centimeter deep.
حفرت في كعب قدمي بعمق سنتيمتر.
Now, you might think of these as anomalies.
الآن، ستعتقدون أن هذه حالات شاذة.
But there is a method to this madness.
ولكن هناك طريقة لهذا الجنون.
I call this "frugal science" --
وأنا أدعوه "العلم الاقتصادي"..
the idea of sharing the experience of science,
فكرة مشاركة تجربة العلم،
and not just the information.
وليس فقط المعلومات.
To remind you:
ولتذكيركم:
there are a billion people on this planet
يوجد مليار شخص على هذا الكوكب
who live with absolutely no infrastructure:
يعيشون بدون بُنى تحتية
no roads,
لا طرقات،
no electricity
لا كهرباء،
and thus, no health care.
وبالتالي، لا رعاية صحية.
Also, there a billion kids on this planet that live in poverty.
أيضًا، هناك مليار طفل على هذا الكوكب يعيشون في الفقر.
How are we supposed to inspire them
كيف يفترض بنا أن نُلهم
for the next generation of solution makers?
الجيل التالي من صناع الحلول؟
There are health care workers that we put on the line
هناك عمال الرعاية الصحية الذين وضعناهم
to fight infectious diseases,
لمكافحة الأمراض المُعدية،
to protect us with absolutely bare-minimum tools and resources.
لكى نحمى أنفسنا ببعض الأدوات والموارد البسيطة
So as a lab at Stanford,
لذا، كأحد المختبرات في ستانفورد
I think of this from a context of frugal science
أفكر في ذلك من منظور العلم الاقتصادي
and building solutions for these communities.
وبناء الحلول لهذه المجتمعات.
Often we think about being able to do diagnosis under a tree, off-grid.
نفكر في القدرة على عمل تشخيص تحت شجرة خارج نطاق الشبكات.
I'll tell you two examples today of new tools.
سأخبركم اليوم عن مثالين من الأدوات الجديدة.
One of them starts in Uganda.
الأولى بدأت في أوغندا.
In 2013,
في عام 2013،
on a field trip to detect schistosomiasis with Foldscopes,
في رحلة ميدانية للكشف عن مرض البلهارسيا بواسطة الفولدسكوب،
I made a minor observation.
أدليت بملاحظة بسيطة.
In a clinic,
في عيادة،
in a far, remote area,
في منطقة نائية،
I saw a centrifuge being used as a doorstop.
رأيت جهاز الطرد المركزي يُستخدم كحاجز للباب.
I mean -- quite literally, the doorstop.
حاجز للباب.. بكل معنى الكلمة.
And I asked them and they said,
وعندما سألتهم، قالوا
"Oh, we don't actually have electricity,
"آه، ليس لدينا كهرباء في الواقع،
so this piece of junk is good as a doorstop."
لذلك رأينا أن قطعة الخردة هذه ستصلح كحاجز للباب".
Centrifuges, for some of you who don't know,
أجهزة الطرد المركزي، للذين لا يعرفونها منكم،
are the pinnacle tool to be able to do sample processing.
عبارة عن أداة قادرة على تجهيز العينة،
You separate components of blood or body fluids
يمكنكم من خلالها فصل مكونات الدم أو سوائل الجسم
to be able to detect and identify pathogens.
للكشف وتحديد مُسببات المرض.
But centrifuges are bulky, expensive --
لكن أجهزة الطرد المركزي كبيرة، ومكلفة..
cost around 1,000 dollars --
تكلفتها حوالي 1000 دولار..
and really hard to carry out in the field.
ويصعب حملها للعمل بالخارج.
And of course,
وطبعًا،
they don't work without power.
لا تعمل بدون طاقة،
Sound familiar?
هل تبدو مألوفة؟
So we started thinking about solving this problem,
لذلك بدأنا التفكير لحل هذه المشكلة،
and I came back --
وعُدت..
kept thinking about toys.
أفكر في الألعاب.
Now ...
الآن..
I have a few with me here.
لدي القليل هنا.
I first started with yo-yos ...
بدأت أول مرة بلعبة "اليويو"
and I'm a terrible yo-yo thrower.
وأنا قاذفٌ رهيب لليويو.
Because these objects spin,
لأن هذه الأشياء تدور،
we wondered,
تساءلنا،
could we actually use the physics of these objects
هل يمكننا استخدام فيزياء هذه الأشياء
to be able to build centrifuges?
لنكون قادرين على بناء أجهزة الطرد المركزي؟
This was possibly the worst throw I could make.
ربما هذه أسوأ رمية أديتها.
But you might start realizing,
لكن قد تبدأون في إدراك،
if you start exploring the space of toys --
إن بدأتم استكشاف الحيز الآمن للألعاب
we tried these spinning tops,
قمنا بتجربة ألعاب الغزل هذه
and then in the lab,
حينها في المختبر
we stumbled upon this wonder.
تعثرنا بهذه الأعجوبة
It's the whirligig, or a buzzer, or a rundle.
وهي الدوامة، أو الطنانة
A couple of strings and a little disk,
زوج من الخيوط وقرص صغير
and if I push, it spins.
وإذا سحبت الخيط تدور
How many of you have played with this as a kid?
كم منكم لعب بهذه في طفولته؟
This is called a button-on-a-string.
هذه تدعى زر على خيط.
OK, maybe 50 percent of you.
حسنًا، ربما نصف الحضور.
What you didn't realize --
ما لم تدركوه
that this little object
هو أن هذا الغرض الصغير
is the oldest toy in the history of mankind ...
هو أقدم لعبة في تاريخ البشر..
5,000 years ago.
منذ 5000 عام مضت.
We have found relics of this object hidden around on our planet.
عثرنا على آثار منها مخبأة في أنحاء الكوكب.
Now the irony is,
المثير للسخرية الآن
we actually don't understand how this little thing works.
هو أننا لا نفهم حقًّا كيف يعمل هذا الشيء.
That's when I get excited.
هذا ما أعطاني شعورًا بالإثارة.
So we got back to work,
لذا عدنا إلى العمل،
wrote down a couple of equations.
وقمنا بكتابة بعض المعادلات.
If you take the input torque that you put in,
إذا احتسبتم العزم الذي ندخله
you take the drag on this disc,
والسحب على القرص
and the twist drag on these strings,
وسحب اللف على هذه الخيوط،
you should be able to mathematically solve this.
ينبغي أن تكونوا قادرين على حل المعادلة.
This is not the only equation in my talk.
وهي ليست المعادلة الوحيدة في حديثي.
Ten pages of math later,
بعد عشر صفحات أخرى من الرياضيات،
we could actually write down the complete analytical solution
تمكنّا من كتابة الحل التحليلي الكامل
for this dynamic system.
لهذا النظام الديناميكي.
And out comes what we call "Paperfuge."
وأصبح لدينا ما ندعوه "الطارد الورقي".
That's my postdoc Saad Bhamla,
هذا هو سعد باملا،
who's the co-inventor of Paperfuge.
شريكي في ابتكار الطارد الورقي.
And to the left, you see all the centrifuges
وإلي اليسار يمكنكم رؤية جميع أجهزة الطرد المركزي
that we're trying to replace.
التي نحاول استبدالها.
This little object that you see right here
هذا الغرض الصغير الذي ترونه هنا
is a disc, a couple of strings and a handle.
عبارة عن قرص وزوج من الخيوط ومقبض.
And when I spin
وعندما أغزله
and I push,
وأبدأ بالسحب
it starts to spin.
يبدأ بالدوران.
Now, when you realize,
الآن، عندما تدركون،
when you do the math,
عندما تقومون بالحساب،
when we calculate the rpm for this object,
عندما نحسب عدد اللفات في الدقيقة لهذا الشيء،
mathematically, we should be able to go all the way to a million rpm.
رياضيًّا، ينبغي أن نكون قادرين على بلوغ مليون لفه بالدقيقة.
Now, there is a little twist in human anatomy,
الآن، هناك أمر متعلق بالتشريح البشري
because the resonant frequency of this object is about 10 hertz,
لأن تردد الرنين لهذا الغرض هو 10 هرتز،
and if you've ever played the piano,
وإذا سبق لكم عزف البيانو
you can't go higher than two or three hertz.
تعلمون أنه لا يمكنكم تحقيق تردد أعلى من 2-3 هرتز.
The maximum speed we've been able to achieve with this object
فإن السرعة القصوى التي أمكننا تحقيقها مع هذا الغرض
is not 10,000 rpm,
ليست 10,000 لفة بالدقيقة
not 50,000 rpm --
أو 50,000 لفة بالدقيقة..
120,000 rpm.
ولكن 120,000 لفة بالدقيقة.
That's equal to 30,000 g-forces.
وهذا يساوي 30,000 على مقياس قوة الجاذبية.
If I was to stick you right here and have it spin,
إذا قمت بوضع أحدكم هنا وجعلتها تدور،
you would think about the types of forces you would experience.
سوف تفكرون في أنواع القوى التي ستؤثر عليكم.
One of the factors of a tool like this
أحد العوامل في أداة مثل هذه
is to be able to do diagnosis with this.
هو أن تكون صالحة لأداء تشخيص بها.
So, I'm going to do a quick demo here, where --
لذلك، سأقدم عرضًا توضيحيًّا سريعًا هنا..
this is a moment where I'm going to make a little finger prick,
هذه اللحظة التي سأقوم فيها بوخز إصبعي هنا
and a tiny drop of blood is going to come out.
وستخرج قطرة صغيرة من الدماء.
If you don't like blood, you don't have to look at it.
إذا كنتم لا تحبون الدماء فلا تنظروا.
Here is a little lancet.
ها هو مبضع صغير.
These lancets are available everywhere,
هذه المباضع متوفرة في كل مكان،
completely passive.
سلبي تمامًا.
And if I've had breakfast today ...
لو أنني تناولت الإفطار اليوم..
That didn't hurt at all.
هذا لم يؤلم مطلقًا.
OK, I take a little capillary with a drop of blood --
حسنًا، سوف آخذ أنبوبًا شِعريًّا مع قطرة من الدم..
now this drop of blood has answers,
وهذه القطرة من الدم تحمل الإجابات
that's why I'm interested in it.
لهذا أنا مهتم بها.
It might actually tell me whether I have malaria right now or not.
فيمكنها أن تخبرني إن كنت مصابًا بالملاريا أم لا.
I take a little capillary,
سوف آخذ الأنبوب الشِعري
and you see it starts wicking in.
وترون أنها بدأت تدخل.
I'm going to draw a little more blood.
سوف أسحب المزيد من الدماء.
And that's good enough for right now.
وهذا كاف الآن.
Now, I just seal this capillary by putting it in clay.
الآن سوف أغلق الأنبوب الشِعري بوضعه في الطمي.
And now that's sealed the sample.
وقد تم غلق العينة.
We're going to take the sample,
سوف نأخذ العينة،
mount it on Paperfuge.
ونثبتها على الطارد الورقي
A little piece of tape to make a sealed cavity.
بقطعة صغيرة من الشريط اللاصق.
So now the sample is completely enclosed.
والآن تم احتواء العينة بالكامل،
And we are ready for a spin.
ونحن جاهزون للتدوير.
I'm pushing and pulling with this object.
أنا أسحب وأدفع هذا الغرض.
I'm going to load this up ...
سوف أقوم بشحن هذه..
And you see the object starts spinning.
وترون أنها بدأت تدور.
Unlike a regular centrifuge,
على عكس جهاز الطرد المركزي،
this is a counter-rotating centrifuge.
هذا طارد عاكس للاتجاه.
It goes back and forth, back and forth ...
فهو يدور للأمام والخلف ثم الأمام والخلف..
And now I'm charging it up,
والآن أقوم بشحنه،
and you see it builds momentum.
وسوف ترون أنه يراكم الدفع.
And now -- I don't know if you can hear this --
والآن، لا أعلم إن كان بإمكانكم سماعه..
30 seconds of this,
بعد 30 ثانية من فعل ذلك،
and I should be able to separate all the blood cells with the plasma.
سأصبح قادرًا على فصل خلايا الدم عن البلازما.
And the ratio of those blood cells to plasma --
ونسبة خلايا الدم إلى البلازما..
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Already, if you see right here,
إذا رأيتم هنا،
if you focus on this,
لو قمنا بالتركيز عليها،
you should be able to see a separated volume
سوف ترون حيزًا مفصولًا
of blood and plasma.
من الدم والبلازما.
And the ratio of that actually tells me whether I might be anemic.
والنسبة بينهما تخبرني باحتمال إصابتي بالأنيميا.
One of the aspects of this is, we build many types of Paperfuges.
وأحد الجوانب هنا هو أننا نبني أنواعًا عديدة من الطارد الورقي.
This one allows us to identify malaria parasites
فهذا يمكننا من الكشف عن الملاريا
by running them for a little longer,
عن طريق تدويره لمدة أطول،
and we can identify malaria parasites that are in the blood
ويمكننا الكشف عن طفيل الملاريا بالدم
that we can separate out and detect with something like a centrifuge.
الذي يمكننا فصله واكتشافه باستخدام جهاز طرد مركزي.
Another version of this allows me to separate nucleic acids
نسخة أخرى تمكننا من فصل الأحماض النووية
to be able to do nucleic acid tests out in the field itself.
لنتمكن من إجراء اختبارات الأحماض النووية في الموقع
Here is another version that allows me to separate bulk samples,
وهنا نسخة أخرى تمكنني من فصل العينات السائبة،
and then, finally,
وأخيرًا،
something new that we've been working on
شيء جديد كنا نعمل عليه
to be able to implement the entire multiplex test on an object like this.
حتى نصبح قادرين على تطبيق كامل الاختبار المتعدد بهذا الغرض.
So where you do the sample preparation and the chemistry in the same object.
حيث يمكن تجهيز العينة واستخدام الكيمياء بنفس الغرض.
Now ...
الآن..
this is all good,
هذا جيد تمامًا،
but when you start thinking about this,
ولكن عند التفكير بالأمر،
you have to share these tools with people.
ينبغي مشاركة هذه الأدوات مع الناس.
And one of the things we did is -- we just got back from Madagascar;
وأحد الأشياء التي قمنا بها.. حيث عدنا حديثًا من مدغشقر؛
this is what clinical trials for malaria look like --
وهذا ما تبدو عليه التجارب السريرية للملاريا..
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You can do this while having coffee.
يمكنك فعل ذلك أثناء تناول القهوة.
But most importantly,
ولكن الأهم من ذلك،
this is a village six hours from any road.
هذه قرية تبعد ست ساعات عن أي طريق.
We are in a room with one of the senior members of the community
نحن في غرفة مع أحد كبار أعضاء المجتمع
and a health care worker.
وعامل بالرعاية الصحية.
It really is this portion of the work that excites me the most --
وهذا الجزء من العمل هو ما يحفزني حقًّا..
that smile,
هذه الابتسامة،
to be able to share simple but powerful tools with people around the world.
أن أكون قادرًا على مشاركة أدوات بسيطة ولكن فعالة مع الناس من أنحاء العالم.
Now, I forgot to tell you this,
نسيت أن أخبركم بأمر،
that all of that cost me 20 cents to make.
وهو أن كل ذلك كلفني 20 سنت لصنعه.
OK, in the negative time I have left,
حسنًا في الوقت السالب الذي تبقى لي
I'll tell you about the most recent --
سوف أخبركم بأحدث..
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
invention from our lab.
ابتكار من مختبري.
It's called Abuzz --
وهو يدعى الطنان [أباز]..
the idea that all of you could help us fight mosquitoes;
والفكرة هي أنكم جميعًا يمكن أن تساهموا في مكافحة البعوض؛
you could all help us track our enemies.
يمكنكم المساهمة في تتبع عدونا.
These are enemies because they cause malaria, Zika, chikungunya, dengue.
هؤلاء أعداؤنا لأنهم يسببون الملاريا وزيكا وحمى شيكونغونيا والدنك.
But the challenge is that we actually don't know where our enemies are.
ولكن التحدي هو أننا لا نعلم أين أعداءنا.
The world map for where mosquitoes are is missing.
لا توجد خريطة عالمية لتواجد البعوض.
So we started thinking about this.
لذلك بدأنا التفكير بالأمر.
There are 3,500 species of mosquitoes,
يوجد 3,500 نوع من البعوض،
and they're all very similar.
وجميعها متشابهة للغاية.
Some of them are so identical
وبعضها متطابقة في الشكل
that even an entomologist cannot identify them under a microscope.
حتى أن عالم حشرات لا يمكنه تمييزها تحت المجهر.
But they have an Achilles' heel.
ولكنها تملك كعب أخيل.
This is what mosquitoes flirting with each other looks like.
هكذا يبدو البعوض عندما تغازل بعضها.
That's a male chasing a female.
هذا ذكر يطارد أنثى.
They're actually talking to each other with their wingbeat frequencies.
إنهم يتحادثون بتردد ضربات أجنحتها.
(Buzzing sound)
(صوت طنين)
And thus, they have a signature.
وبذلك، فهي تملك توقيعًا.
We realized that using a regular phone,
ونحن ندرك أن استخدام هاتف عادي،
a $5-10 flip phone --
هاتف ثمنه من 5 إلى 10 دولار..
how many remember what this object is?
كم منكم يتذكر هذا؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We can record these acoustic signatures from mosquitoes.
يمكننا تسجيل هذه التوقيعات الصوتية من البعوض.
I'll tell you exactly how to do this.
سوف أخبركم بكيفية فعل ذلك.
I caught some mosquitoes outside.
أمسكت بعض البعوض بالخارج.
Unlike Bill [Gates], I'm not going to release them.
وبعكس بيل [جيتس] لا أنوي إطلاقهم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But I will tell you how to record from this.
ولكن سأخبركم كيف تسجلون لهم.
All you do is tap them and they fly.
كل ما تفعلونه هو جعلها تطير.
You can first test --
يمكنكم اختبارها أولًا..
I can actually hear that.
يمكنني سماع ذلك.
And you bring your phone, which has microphones --
ثم تحضر هاتفك الذي يحوي ميكروفون..
it turns out the mics are so damn good already,
تبين أن هذه الميكروفونات جيدة،
even on regular phones,
حتى في الهواتف العادية،
that you can pick up this near-field signature.
فيمكنكم التقاط هذا التوقيع.
And since I'm out of time,
وحيث قد نفد وقتي
let me just play the recording that I made a day ago.
دعوني أشغل تسجيلًا قمت بإعداده بالأمس.
(Mosquitoes buzz)
(طنين بعوض)
This is all the charming sound that you heard before
هذا هو الصوت الساحر الذي سمعتموه سابقًا
that you all love.
الذي تحبونه جميعًا.
One of the contexts of this
وأحد السياقات هنا
is that being able to do this with a regular cell phone
هو أن إمكانية صنع ذلك بهاتف عادي
allows us to map mosquito species.
يسمح لنا بعمل خريطة لأنواع البعوض.
Using a flip phone,
باستخدام هاتف يطوى،
we mapped one of the largest acoustic databases
قمنا بعمل أكبر قاعدة بيانات صوتية
with 25 to 20 species of mosquitoes that carry human pathogens.
ل 20 إلى 25 نوع من البعوض تحمل مسببات الأمراض البشرية.
And from this and machine learning,
وبهذا وبالإضافة إلى تعلم الآلة،
anybody who uploads this data,
وأي شخص يقوم بتحميل هذه البيانات،
we can identify and tell the probability
يمكننا تعريف احتمال
of what species of mosquitoes you're actually working with.
أي نوع من البعوض تعمل معه.
We call this Abuzz, and if any of you want to sign up,
ونحن ندعو ذلك الطنان [أباز] وإذا أراد أي منكم التسجيل،
just go to the website.
فليذهب إلى الموقع الإلكتروني.
Let me close with something
دعوني أنهي بقول شيء
that's very important and dear to my heart.
هام للغاية وعزيز على قلبي:
One of the challenges of today is we have terrible problems.
أحد التحديات اليوم أننا نملك مشاكل كبرى،
We have a billion people with absolutely no health care,
مثل وجود مليار شخص دون رعاية صحية،
climate change, biodiversity loss,
التغير المناخي، وفقدان التنوع البيولوجي،
on and on and on.
والمزيد.
And we hope that science is going to provide the answer.
ونحن نأمل أن العلم يمكنه توفير الحلول.
But before you leave this theatre today,
ولكن قبل مغادرة هذا المسرح اليوم،
I want you to promise one thing.
أريدكم أن تعدوني بشيء..
We're going to make science accessible --
أننا سوف نجعل العلم متاحًا
not just to the people who can afford it,
ليس فقط للأشخاص الذين يمكنهم تحمل كلفته
but a billion others who can't.
ولكن لمليارات آخرين لا يمكنهم ذلك.
Let's make science and scientific literacy a human right.
دعونا نجعل العلم والثقافة العلمية أحد حقوق الإنسان.
The moment that you pass the tingling feeling of making a discovery
اللحظة التي تمرر فيها شعور تحقيق كشف جديد
to another child,
إلى طفل آخر،
you're enabling them to be the next group of people
بذلك تمكنونهم من أن يصبحوا المجموعة القادمة من الأشخاص
who will actually solve these problems.
الذين سوف يقومون بحل هذه المشاكل.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)